<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King and both houses of Parliament sitting at Westminster, and to every particular member thereof this is a timely warning that they do not make laws against the righteous and innocent people of the Lord called Quakers, as the unrighteous rulers whom God overthrew before them, did / by Humphrey Wolrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12596577</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12596577</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the King and both houses of Parliament sitting at Westminster, and to every particular member thereof this is a timely warning that they do not make laws against the righteous and innocent people of the Lord called Quakers, as the unrighteous rulers whom God overthrew before them, did / by Humphrey Wolrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64061:1"/>
            <p>TO THE KING and both Houſes of PARLIAMENT ſitting at VVeſtminſter, And to every particular Member thereof; This is a timely warning that they do not make Laws againſt the Righteous and Innocent People of the Lord called Quakers, as the unrighteous Rulers whom God overthrew before them, did.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pro. <hi>20.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The King that ſitteth in the Throne of Jugdement, ſcattereth away all evil with his eyes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Humphrey Wolrich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon</hi> at the ſign of the Black ſpread Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle and Windmil in <hi>Martins le Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64061:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64061:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>O Parliament.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DO not ye eſtabliſh that which the Lord hath determined to overthrow, neither do ye endeavour to deſtroy by unrighteous Laws, Truth which the Lord hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to eſtabliſh, and his worſhip in Spirit will he exalt, and all other worſhip taught by the precepts and commandements of men are abomination, and the Lord will overturn and root it out of this Land in his ſeaſon; and though Idolatry be taking root, and ſpreading it ſelf over this Land as the branches of a green bay tree, yet the Lord will ariſe, and his enemies ſhall be ſcattered as the chaffe of the threſhing floor before the wind, and the whirlwind of the Lord ſhall fling them out of their place, for the Lord hath a mighty and a ſtrong One, whom Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Councils and Parliaments have too too much rejected, and ſet at naught, and the wiſe builders in all ages, yet a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in all generations hath he ſaved, and to them hath he been a tryed ſtone, elect and precious, and to the generation of the righteous who have ſought the Lord in all ages, hath he been a rock, a ſhelter, and hiding place, and a ſure foundation unto them where they have been hid from the perſecution and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of men, even of ſuch men which would not have them to rule over them, ſuch in all ages have been making Laws, and ſealing unrighteous decrees againſt the innocent, to bind the Conſciences of the Servants of the Lord that they might not worſhip him in the liberty of his own Spirit, ſuch would never own Chriſt (the light) in their Conſciences which ſaith, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye the ſame unto them) for their Lord, King, and Lawgiver: For thus ſaith the Lord, it is <hi>by me that Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice, by me Princes rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the earth,</hi> Prov. 8.14. <hi>I wiſdom dwell with prudence, and find our knowledge of witty invention.</hi> Friends, this is ſpoken of Chriſt, who is the wiſdom and power of God, and in whom are found treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge, who ſaith counſel is mine, and ſound wiſdom, I am underſtanding, I have ſtrength, this is he who hath given a meaſure of his true Light into all your Conſciences to be your Counſellor, this is the power of God, to which every ſoul muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64061:3"/>be ſubject, and every one that would act for God in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt take counſel at this Spirit which ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty, and judgeth among the gods, who is for a Spirit of judgment to him that ſitteth in judgment, and whoſe name is called wonderful Counſellor, the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of peace; (mark) this is he which ſaith <hi>open thy mouth for the dumb, in the cauſe of all ſuch as are appointed unto deſtruction, open thy mouth, judge righteouſly, and plead the cauſe of the poor and needy;</hi> this is he of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11 from the 2. to the 5. <hi>the Spirit of the Lord ſhall reſt upon him, the Spirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, the ſpirit of counſel and might, the ſpirit of knowledge, and of the fear of the Lord, and ſhall make him of quick underſtanding in the fear of the Lord, he ſhall not judge after the ſight of his eyes neither reprove after the hearing of his ears, but with righteouſneſſe ſhall he judge the poor, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth, and righteouſneſſe ſhall be the girdle of his loins, and faithfulneſſe the girdle of his rains,</hi> this is he which <hi>Job</hi> put on as a garment, <hi>Job</hi> 29 14. <hi>I put on Righteouſneſſe and it cloathed me, my judgement was as a robe and diadem;</hi> (mark) this was the light by which <hi>Job</hi> walked through darkneſſe, and a Spirit of judgement when he ſate in judgment, the Princes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained talking before him, the Nobles held their peace, and their tongues cleaved to the roof of their mouths when the ear heard me, mark, <hi>bleſſed is the ear that hears, and the eye that ſees, for they are ſatisfied,</hi> then it bleſſed me, and when the eye ſaw me it gave witneſſe to me; Friends mind the teſtimony of God and have the witneſſe in your ſelves, as <hi>Job</hi> had, who ſaid, <hi>I hold faſt my righteouſneſſe, my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live, becauſe I delivered the poor that cryed, and I cauſed the widows heart to ſing for joy: I was alſo eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame, I was a Father to the poor, and the cauſe which I knew not I ſearched out, I brake the jaws of the wicked, and pluckt the ſpoil out of their teeth; unto me men gave ear, and kept ſilent at my counſel, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for my words as for the latter rain;</hi> [mark] here was no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining when true judgement did run down as a ſtream, then was the door of the priſoner opened, and the widows heart did ſing for joy, then did truth ſpring out of the earth, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe rained down from Heaven, then did the branch of righteouſneſſe grow, and the arm of the poor was ſtrengthned, and the high arm of the wicked was alſo broken, then did glory
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64061:3"/>ſpread it ſelf, and the life was revealed as in the dayes of old, when <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God judged the tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So Friends, many eyes are waiting upon you, the many eyes of the Beaſt which the Lord will blind are looking for ſome unrighteous decree, that the Merchants of <hi>Babylon</hi> in whom the cry of the righteous is great, and in whom the bloud of the Innocent hath cryed for vengeance, their eyes are looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and their expectations are great, that ye will ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their falſe worſhip by a Law, which if you do, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all to worſhip in a form which is now ſetting up, utterly contrary to the Scriptures, and form and power of godlineſſe, the Lord will deſtroy and confound you and them together; For he hath determined, the Lord hath ſaid, and will moſt certainly bring it to paſſe, that he will be as an enemy, and ſtand with his everlaſting arm as an adverſary againſt all that would bind the Conſciences of thoſe that fear the Lord, or by any Law or Decree would compell to worſhip in any form, but in that which his own Spirit leadeth into, the Lord hath ſaid it, and his word is ſetled and eſtabliſhed as a Decree for ever, that he will overturn all falſe worſhip, and all ſuch as have a name of Miniſters of Chriſt, but are found in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> running after rewards, and ſeeking their gain, each one from his quarter, whoſe God is their bellies, and who mind earthly things, and whoſe end is deſtruction, the Lord hath ſaid it.</p>
            <p>Alſo the eyes of the Innocent are towards you, and though our expectation be to the Lord for deliverance, yet we know right well, that the coming in of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of you together by him, is not without his hand; and as we are free born Engliſh men, we have juſt cauſe to expect ſo much from You, that we ſhould not lie in Hoſes, Priſons and Dungeons as we have done, and be kept in ſlavery in the Land of our Nativity, many of us have been Priſoners very long, for the breach of no manner of Law, and our Perſecutors ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation is, that you will confirm what they have done; but the juſt Lord, whoſe throne is eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſſe, his eye runneth through the Earth, and his eye lids try the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath ſaid, <hi>The Rock of Iſrael ſpake by me, be that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, Ruling in the Fear of God, he ſhall be as the light
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64061:4"/>of the morning when the Sun ariſeth, even a morning with clouds, as the tender Graſs</hi> (mark, as the tender Graſſe) <hi>ſpringing out of the Earth by clear ſhining after rain;</hi> But thus ſaith the Lord, the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> and ſuch as ſet themſelves &amp; the Rulers that take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel together againſt the Lord and againſt his Annointed ſhall be daſhed to pieces as a Potters Veſſel, and foulded up and thruſt together as Briars and Thorns for the burning Furnace; the Lord hath raiſed up a Plant of Renown out of a dry ground which many are ſmiting at, and a Vine moſt dear hath he brought out of <hi>Aegypts</hi> Land, where it grew not well, and many, yes Multitudes and Peoples and Tongues are ſpoiling this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vine and wounding the Branches that ſpring from this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Root, the Lord himſelf hath planted it, and to you this is the word of the Lord, he will pluck up and ſupplant all that would deſtroy it. Wo be to the wicked, it ſhall go ill with them, the reward of their hands ſhall be given them that would deſtroy the Mother with the Children, that take away the cloathing from the naked, and the ſheaf from the hungry, and leave him deſolate that hath no deliverer in the earth.</p>
            <p>To you all that ſit in Parliament, this is a timely warning which the Lord hath put into my heart, and in whoſe good wil and everlaſting love, I put my life in his hand, that I may be clear of your blood, and alſo in the ſight of the Lord which moved me thereunto; and though this be a thing ſcorned by many who are ſetting up a falſe worſhip, to ſpeak of the leadings or movings of Gods Spirit; yet ſhall you have cauſe to confeſs that it was the infallable Spirit of the Lord that cannot lie, which warned you of a ſore deſtruction that is like to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and as ſurely as ever the Lord overturned Parliaments, Committees and Protectors which were Perſecutors of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent before you, ſo moſt certainly will the Lord deal by you, and double as you double your Perſecution and cruelty in binding and wracking by unrighteous Laws, the Conſciences of his Servants and people, the Lord hath ſaid it, the ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will not lie, whoſe word is in my Heart, and whoſe two edged Sword is in my right hand; if ye ſeek to waſte and deſtroy his people, he will waſte your ſtrength, and your might ſhall be mightily to deſtroy one another; and you and your King, for whom I take up a Lamentation, and it may truly be for a Lamentation, that after ſuch an unheard of deliverance,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64061:4"/>which if he did but mind or ſee the hand that was merciful to him, in bringing him to his Throne, and that by his own arm was he wonderfully delivered and redeemed out of many and diverſe tribulations, not by his own Sword or Bow, and ſetled him in a good Land, and planted him in ſo fruitful a ſoil, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own expectation, and when there was none of his Friends could in reaſon look for ſuch a thing, in the time when it was brought to paſſe, that ſo ſoon after the baniſhed was brought back, there ſhould be ſuch unheard of cruelty againſt the Lords people, in ſo much that <hi>England</hi> never ſaw the like; never did <hi>England</hi> ſee its Priſons and Dungeons ſo filled with a people, that were ſo clear from all Plots, Treaſon, Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Plottings and Inſurrections; teſtifie againſt us, ſhew us if you can, have we uſed any Carnal Weapons? Or have our Weapons been Carnal ſince we were a people? Bring in your Witneſſe, and if it be true, we will confeſſe to it; when did we ever cauſe either you or your King to ſuffer by outward force or cruelty? But in Patience and Quietneſſe have we ſuffered by all thoſe Perſecutors which went before you, whoſe meaſure of wickedneſs and cruelty you are filling up apace, that ye may drink the remainder of his Wrath, and the cup of his fury filld and prepared for you, who are ſtanding up like <hi>Amaleck,</hi> that thought to have ſtopt the way of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>Jacobs</hi> Seed ſhould not go into the Land of Reſt, for which cauſe the Lord ſaid, he would root out the name of <hi>Amaleck</hi> from under Heaven; and I ſay concerning you; ye ſhall never be eſtabliſhed, neither ſhall you proſper, but your own doings ſhall purſue you, and (the ſwift Witneſſe of God) the Light in your conſciences ſhall condemn you ſo long as you are Fighting and Warring againſt the Lambs of Chriſt, and perſecuting a people whom the Lord hath bleſſed, and the Lord hath promiſed, and his promiſes are ſure to the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> throughout all Generations, the Seed is Chriſt the Light, this whom the Lord hath ſaid ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe abundantly; he it is that goes before us, the ſhout of a King is in the midſt of us, he will be with us and ſave us, and for his own Name ſake he will not leave us nor forſake us; Therefore are we not diſmaled, though we are perſecuted, yet are we not forſaken of him, who hath ſaid, <hi>fear not, I the Lord am the ſame and change not, I the Lord kill and make alive, I bring to the Grave, I the Lord open the door of the Priſoner, and my ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64061:5"/>arm is underneath to lift him out of the pit; Ile preak to pieces, Ile daſh to pieces ſaith the Rock of Iſrael them that looſe not the band of the oppreſſed and opens not the door of the priſoner;</hi> God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and his everlaſting Decree is ſealed &amp; eſtabliſhed, as the earth which cannot be moved, that Chriſt ſhall reign in the midſt of his enemies, Righteouſneſſe, Truth and equity ſhall the earth be filled withal as the waters cover the Sea, God hath ſaid it, his people he will ſave that are appointed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, his Lambs will he carry in his everlaſting arm whom the Wolves, Bears and Lions ſeek to devour.</p>
            <p>We hear the voice of God as his Sheep alwaies did (though this may be counted blaſphemy with the perſecutors, which never heard his voice themſelves, nor ſaw his ſhape at any time, and this was <hi>Daniels</hi> God, the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> the God of <hi>Shedrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> the God of <hi>Mordecai</hi> who was a Jew inwardly, the God of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of all the Fathers who dyed in the faith, and in obedience to the Lord, not fearing the wrath of the Kings and Rulers who have ſet themſelves in all ages againſt the Lord and his Annointed, and hidden ones; theſe all dyed in the faith which the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor is out of, of whom it is ſaid <hi>Heb</hi> 11. <hi>the world was not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of,</hi> and as <hi>John</hi> the beloved of the Father ſaith concerning himſelf, and they that had fellowſhip with him, <hi>the world knows us not, therefore doth the world hate us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe had cruel mockings and ſcourgings, conſider this ye that ought to do Juſtice and break the bands of oppreſſion: Oh! conſider ye Parliament men, to you am I moved of the Lord to write, There is work enough for you to do in <hi>England</hi> to ſtop the ſwearers mouth and the floud of wickedneſſe that is overflowing this Nation; this is not your work to tread upon the conſciences of men that cannot ſwear at all; Conſcience is Gods Throne, and the place where his Honor dwelleth is the lowly heart, and the Lord will not give his Glory to another, neither muſt any but himſelf who is the God of the Spirits of all fleſh preſcribe his children a way to worſhip the Father of Spirits in, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him not in Spirit, Chriſt ſaith, they worſhip they know not what;</hi> Now little doth the perſecutor know what he is doing, who is juſtifying the wicked, and condemning the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous whom the Lord doth juſtifie in not Swearing, in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64061:5"/>to Chriſts Command, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> this is a thing very pleaſing to the Lord, who is that Spirit of Truth, and lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men to ſpeak the Truth, and do that to their Neighbours and all men, as they would have men do unto them with-without Swearing; and have ye not read in the Scripturs, that the Kings Throne is eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs! And is not Chriſt the Prince of Peace and King of Righteouſneſſe! And do you believe that this is like to eſtabliſh King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to impriſon ſo many thouſands as he hath done, becauſe they cannot break the Righteous Commands of Chriſt by Swearing at all? Is it better to obey God or man, judge ye with the meaſure of his own Light? Is not this to be ſubject to the higher power, which power is a terror to the evil doer, to obey the Commands of Chriſt, who is the Power and Wiſdom of God, unto whom all Power in Heaven and Earth is given? Do ye believe that all your Souls, and the Soul of King <hi>Charles</hi> ought not to be ſubject to Chriſt? Or do you believe your Power is above his, becauſe ſo many thouſands are Impriſoned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot break the Command of Chriſt, whoſe Spirit ſpake in <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> For Rulers are not a terror to good works but to evil (mark) Chriſt ſaith <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Ye have heard ſay by them of old time, thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but I ſay unto you ſwear not at all,</hi> verſ. 37. <hi>but let your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication be yea, yea, nay, nay; for what is more cometh of evil;</hi> alſo read <hi>James</hi> 5 verſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Above all things my Brethren Swear not;</hi> Now I believe you will not deny but that Chriſt and <hi>James</hi> an Apoſtle of his were truly obedient to Magiſtrates in that which was meet, and that their Souls alſo were ſubject to God; and though <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>an Oath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men was on end of ſtrife;</hi> yet it is plain, it was not ſo among the Brethren that were in Chriſt Jeſus, the word of the Oath, which was ſince the Law, and puts an end to all ſtrife which the Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are in, and againſt which the Law and Oaths were added, until (the Seed) Chriſt came who is the end of them both for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake; for the Law was not added againſt a Righteous man, but againſt the wicked, the lawleſſe and diſobedient.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that Rule well are worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> and do you believe in your Conſciences, that they which rule for God, will ever be a terrour to ſuch as for Conſcience ſake dare not break the Commands of his Son, of whom he hath ſaid, <hi>all ſhall hearken unto;</hi> and though (Angels) Prophets, and the Fathers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64061:6"/>which were under a Cloud in the dayes of old did Swear, yet Chriſt was greater then the Prophets and before <hi>Abraham;</hi> and when he was brought forth into the world, it was ſaid (and <hi>the VVord of the Lord endures for ever) Let all the Angels of God worſhip him,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and this I ſay, neither I nor any of us deny Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from any thing that is in our Hearts againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> or his Government, or that we cannot willingly be ſubject to any of his Righteous Commands (and that for Conſcience ſake towards God) but becauſe we are perſwaded in our Hearts and Spirits by the Lord (and not onely ſince King <hi>Charles</hi> came in) that Swearing is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in any caſe, becauſe it is contrary to his Command, by Chriſt his Son, whom he hath ſaid all muſt hearken to, but this hath been our Principle to deny Swearing, for which we were perſecuted by all the Governours that went before you for many years.</p>
            <p>But ye may conſider, were they not ſuch as did Swear to be true to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, that afterwards cut off his head? Were they not ſuch who Swore to be true to King and Parliament, that afterwards proved the greateſt enemies to them both? Time would fail me to mention all the Treacheries that have been wrought in <hi>England</hi> within this twenty years, by ſuch as have taken Oaths and Covenants to the contrary; in a few words Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Swear not, but ſpeak the Truth, and whatſoever ye would have men do unto you, do ye the ſame to them, and thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> and he that doth this is the end of the Law, and greater then the Prophets which did Swear, which thing we have laboured to do, both in the light of God and men, not in our own ſtrength, for we are nothing but in the Name of our Lord Jeſus who bears up our heads in our Sufferings, and is our all in tribulation, for whoſe Names ſake we Suffer patiently, praying to the Lord that he would forgive them which know not what they do; and we have the teſtimony and the ſure witneſſe of the Lord in our Conſciences, that we do not ſuffer as Thieves, Murderers and evil doers, neither are we guilty of the breach of any good Law of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s, but onely in this are we looked upon as guilty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we meet together to Worſhip the Lord as his Spirit leadeth us, the King having commanded the contrary, which Law ſhould I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak more, I bear my Teſtimony againſt as unrighteous; for as Children newly born are we clear from all plottings, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King or any other Government, ſince we were a people called of the Lord, not to fight with Carnal weapons as many have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64061:6"/>done, but with Spiritual Weapons which have been mighty through God, not to the deſtroying of mens Bodies, but the bringing down and deſtroying of that wicked ſpirit which hath captivated, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and deſtroyed the Creation of God, under which the whole Creation travelleth in pain, and groaneth greatly, waiting for the redemption and manifeſtation of the Son of God, who comes not to deſtroy the World or mens lives, but the works of the Devil, which have been wrought in man, whereby mans life hath been a burthen too heavy for himſelf to bear; And the Lord hath raiſed us up, and we are his witneſſes againſt all hireling Prieſts which Preach for hire, and we bear our teſtimony, and it is the Lords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all falſe Prophets which are in the was of <hi>Balaam,</hi> runing gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily after rewards; theſe are they which withſtand the Lord and his people, and though they ſay they are Miniſters of Chriſt, yet we teſtifie by the Spirit of the Lord, that they are no better then the falſe Prophets which <hi>Jeremiah, Eſay</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> cryed againſt, and ſuch as <hi>Paul, Phillip.</hi> 3. complained of verſ. 18. <hi>For many walk of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt. Whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their Belly, whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly things.</hi> Theſe are they which the Lords controverſie is againſt, and againſt whom he will ſtand as an adverſary, until he have deſtroyed them, Root and Branch; and as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe men withſtand the Truth; (Mark) How did they withſtand <hi>Moſes?</hi> not by denying the ſigns and wonders which he wrought, but by doing lying wonders, by the enchantments and witchcraft which <hi>Moſes</hi> did by the Power and finger of God, ſo theſe men whom <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath taken for Miniſters of Chriſt, even theſe men which have run to every Power, King and Parliament to eſtabliſh them a Law for their Bellies, theſe men do not reſiſt the Truth, in denying Prayer, Singing and Preaching, and ſuch things as the Spirit of God led the Saints to formerly, but by living in the form of them, and Singing, Preaching and Praying by the Spirit of the World, as their Fruits make them manifeſt, to have another Spirit, then what the True Miniſters and Prophets of God had, which is not of the Father, but of the World; When did you ever read in all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that the true Miniſters did run to the Magiſtrates for their bellies, as this generation of falſe teachers for many hundreds of years have done? When Chriſt ſent forth his Miniſters to preach, he bid them go and enquire in the Towns and Cities where they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64061:7"/>came who was worthy, and ſuch things as they ſet before them they were to eat, this was their hire and maintenance which Chriſt the chief Biſhop did allow them, for ſaith he, <hi>the Labourer is worthy of his meat,</hi> he did not bid them go into ſuch a Town or City, and bargain by ſo much a year, or how much will you give me and I'le be your Miniſter, but ſaith he freely have you received, freely give; Is not <hi>Englands</hi> Miniſtery and their gift of preaching bought in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ſold in Cities and Countries all over this Nation; ſo that which can be ſold &amp; bought for mony is not the gift of God, for all the gifts and graces of God are free and freely to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, as they are freely given, and not ſold for money; So you may read <hi>Acts</hi> 8.20. where <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer would have bought the gift of God for money, <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou thoughteſt the gift of God can be purchaſed with money. Balaam</hi> the Sorcerer who had the gift of God freely given him (a thing which the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> know not, but are enemies thereunto) he ſaw the goodly Tents of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the pleaſant dwelling place of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but his heart being divided he would have ſold the gift of God for money, and the gift which God gave him freely, if he could have done it by his inchantments, he would have curſed the people whom the Lord had not curſed, and in whom (he himſelf confeſſing) was the voice of a King, and perceived that there was no divination nor inchantment againſt them Therefore he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moans himſelf, and ſays unto <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lak, if thou wouldſt give me thine houſe full of ſilver and gold, I cannot go beyond the Commandment of the Lord;</hi> (Mark) The holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> which will not be limited, limits his enemies; And to you all, this is the word of the Lord, <hi>You ſhall not go beyond your limit, nor deſtroy the people whom the Lord hath bleſſed;</hi> do not harden your hearts againſt the Lord as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, for you have had many warnings by the Servants of the Lord already, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had when he would not let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, but increaſed their bondage, and doubled his cruelty againſt them, and as the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which went before you were often warned of a ſore deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and overthrow that was coming upon them, and though their hands were ſtrong, and the Kingdoms were ſtrengthned in their hands, yet did the Servants of the Lord often warn them and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of all that is now befallen them; And though they could not believe it when it was declared unto them, neither did they relieve the oppreſſed, nor looſe the bands of the priſoner, but as it is in this your day, they waxed obſtinate againſt the Lord, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64061:7"/>hearkned to the falſe Prophets, and hireling Prieſts, which were their ruine, and mocked the Prophets, and abuſed his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which he ſent unto them (becauſe he had compaſſion on his dwelling place) ſo that the wrath of the Lord brake out upon them untill there was no remedy; He gave them up to the ſpoilers as it is this day, and them which were become tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butaries to them hath he brought in ſubjection, and made tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries themſelves; how did they proſper, judge in your ſelves? was any able to ſtand before them; while the Lord was on their ſide, did they not proſper? did not the dread and fear fall upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about? then was there no oppreſſion of the Innocent, nor wounding of tender Conſciences in this Land about Religion, when did they grow weak &amp; feeble, and the mighty men became as women? was it not when they begun to bind the Conſciences of men, &amp; would take upon them the ſeat of God in the Conſcience, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Spirit of the Lord a way and dead form to worſhip in? did they not whip, perſecute and impriſon as ye have done the Servants of the Lord for not ſwearing? and becauſe for Conſcience ſake they could neither hear nor maintain a falſe Miniſtry, in giving them the tenth of their labours, and when the Lord had given them reſt from all thoſe whom they called oppreſſors and tyrants, did they not then ſettle upon their lees, and eſtabliſh themſelves, and take upon them as great things, if not greater, then theſe things which before they had ſo long fought againſt as tyranical? did not the Lord become their enemy then, and was not all their might which they had leſt mightily to confound and overturn one another? were they not then reſtleſſe, and ſilled with diſorder? and did they not ſeek them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that which they called <hi>The good old Cauſe</hi> was wholly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected? did not oppreſſion wax ſtrong, and the cry great in the Land? and did they not begin to get up into the ſeat of God as ye have done, by making unrighteous Laws againſt the innocent?</p>
            <p>Did not God ariſe then as a mighty man, and rob them of their ſtrength, and their ſtrength was wholly to betray and deſtroy one another, ſo that no man could truſt (ſcarcely) his Brother with whom in the day of their ſtraits, and when as one man they cryed to the Lord againſt oppreſſors, they could as one man joyn and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage together? And their lives, gold, and ſilver, lands, wives and children were not dear unto them in that day: But alas! alas! how do I pity them, and in the day of their proſperity, when afterwards they kicked againſt the Lord, how did the ſervants of the Lord
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64061:8"/>mourn over them, and oftentimes warn them, precept upon precept, line upon line, of a diſmal day that was coming upon them; but alas! they would not believe, for their hearts were waxed groſſe; ſo that this Proverb may be truly taken up againſt them; how hath the oppreſſor ceaſed, the golden City ceaſed? the Lord hath broken the ſtaffe of the wicked, and the Scepter of the Rulers.</p>
            <p>And now Friends, this will be your condition, and a lamentation may truly be taken up for you, if you go on as you have begun. God was merciful unto you in bringing you to the Government in peace, without bloudſhed, and his mercy and loving kindneſſe ſhould have engaged you to have been merciful to them which were cut off by you; did the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> bring you from ſo great a captivity that you ſhould go on in a way of cruelty towards them whom the Lord delivered into your hands? Friends, I take my life in my hand, and teſtifie in the name of the Lord, that the foundation of your Government ſhould not have been laid in bloud, but in mercy and righteouſneſſe would your dayes have been prolonged, and your Throne would have been eſtabliſhed as long as the Sun &amp; the Moon endures; but you have reaſoned againſt your own ſouls. Amend your waies, ſeek judgment, &amp; love mercy, that the Lord may repent him of the evil that is near you, and a ſudden deſtruction as a whirlwind from the Lord which will fling you out of your place: Tis mercy &amp; peace when they meet together, cauſeth truth and righteouſneſſe to embrace each other, but violence and cruelty cryeth for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the bloud and oppreſſion of the innocent, for a ſudden deſtruction; now this I teſtifie in the faith of our Lord Jeſus, for whoſe ſake <hi>I</hi> am willing to ſuffer the loſs of all, and from whoſe love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath loved me, <hi>I am perſwaded, neither death, nor life, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, nor powers, ſhall be able to ſeparate me;</hi> This I believe therefore I ſpeak, Kingdoms ſhall be rooted up, Parliaments ſhall not proſper, Councils of men ſhall be confounded by the Lord, and come to nought, that would bow the Conſciences and ſouls of men to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a ſtrange God, or the true God in a falſe manner, or in any other way but what his holy Spirit leadeth unto; God will daſh the pot ſheards and kingdoms of the earth one againſt another, until he make a way, and a way be prepared for the Government and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt in the Conſciences of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people; and this I ſay, if you continue in perſecution of the innocent, that have done you no harm, The Lord will bind you in chains of utter darkneſſe, and in the dark places of the earth will he ſhut you up together, who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64061:8"/>make Laws to bind the Conſciences of his people, which to you and the King have done no harm; for you are not of the ſame mind in theſe things as <hi>Moſes,</hi> that Magiſtrate and Law-giver was, who ſaid, when complaint was made to him, as it is againſt us, for prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſpeaking as the Spirit of the Lord leads us; he anſwered thoſe envious accuſers, and ſaid, Would God all the Lords people were Prophets, and that he would put his Spirit upon them all: Now theſe are enemies who are accuſing us to you, as the falſe Prophets and Prieſts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. who ſaid <hi>Jeremy</hi> was worthy to dye, even theſe are you eſtabliſhing by a Law (which the Lord will break) and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the accuſed which are innocent, and as greatly wronged as ever <hi>Ieremy</hi> was, them are ye preparing war againſt, and making un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous decrees, which the Lord himſelf will break, in the day wherein he maketh inquiſition for the bloud of the innocent, and brings out the priſoner, and ſuch as be oppreſſed out of the priſon-houſe: And as for thoſe Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who make a trade of the ſouls of men for diſhoneſt gain, and bare rule by your means, and laws made for their bellies, And whoever it be that puts not into their mouths, they prepare war againſt him, I have ſeen with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal eye of God their deſtruction is near to come, and their day ſhall not be prolonged, I have ſeen them as a wall whoſe covering is taken away, &amp; every ſtorm &amp; turning of the wind ſhall ſhake them to pieces, as a rotten fence, becauſe they have provoked the Lord to jealouſie, and by grieving his Lambs and Children; and as for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and cruelty there is none like them in this Nation; The Lord hath ſaid, and he will moſt certainly bring it to paſſe, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed as in the day when God created man upon the earth, in which Dominion man was to rule with God, and for God, and not againſt God and his Children, as ye do; who hath heard of ſuch a thing in Chriſtendom as is brought to paſſe in <hi>England,</hi> that ſo many thouſands ſhould be impriſoned, indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the utter ruine of their Families, and the deſtruction of their outward lives, and yet the breach of no juſt Law either of God or man can be juſtly proved or charged againſt us? but onely becauſe we cannot make ſhipwrack of our Conſciences, by violating the righteous command of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, but love your enemies, pray for them that perſecute you and deſpitefully uſe you;</hi> Conſider, is this to love your enemies, to perſecute your friends? is this to be ſubject to God the higher power, your ſelves, to perſecute, impriſon and ſpoil them which cannot break the commands of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64061:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Son of God? O let not ſuch a thing be publiſhed in <hi>Askelon,</hi> nor declared in the ſtreets of <hi>Gath</hi> any more by Chriſtians. O how have you cauſed the uncircumciſed in heart to rejoyce, and let looſe a Sea of cruelty and perſecution over this Nation; May not we truly ſay as <hi>David</hi> did, concerning <hi>Saul,</hi> I ſay may not we ſay the ſame being innocent as he was, whom do you and your King come out againſt with all theſe weapons of cruelty and war, is it not againſt worm in <hi>Jacob</hi> whom God hath bleſſed? As <hi>Saul</hi> came out againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> who in ſpirit ſaid, <hi>I am a worm and no man;</hi> Were not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God ſure to <hi>David,</hi> that he would build him a ſure houſe? and did not the Lord ſay concerning his ſeed, which is Chriſt, <hi>Sit thou at my right hand until I make thy enemies thy footſtool?</hi> Is God chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged now, and is not the ſeed unto which all the promiſes are, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and forever? bleſſed of the Lord, choſen of the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> from generation to generation. What have we done either againſt you or the King, that we have had no other place in the Land of our Nativity, but Holes, Priſons, and Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons? Are not we called by the Name of the Lord, and doth not our ſubjection to you in all lawful things declare that we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent? Why then are we numbred by you, as Chriſt was by the <hi>Jews,</hi> amongſt Tranſgreſſors?</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
